{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Inmates at the Prison of the Annamites in this department revolted against poor conditions in Inini. In the 1880s, this region fought a border-war with Brazil over the independent state of Counani. A man cried \"Long live France! Long live the Army!\" after being sentenced to life imprisonment in a penal colony in this region, from which Henri Charrière [[shah-ree-YAY]] escaped, as recounted in his novel Papillon [[pah-pee-YOHN]]. The European Space Agency constructed its primary space center in , for ten points, what French overseas region, where Alfred Dreyfus was imprisoned on Devil’s Island.",
      "answer": [
        "French Guiana",
        "La Guyane Française"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man is the subject of a work by Joseph Califano titled The Triumph and Tragedy of [this man], and over 400 collections of manuscripts were relied upon by Robert Dalleck in another biography of this man. A four-volume series, including such entries as The Passage of Power and Master of the Senate, was written about this one-time Speaker of the House. For ten points, Robert Caro wrote that four-volume biography of what man who took the presidential oath on an airplane?",
      "answer": [
        "Lyndon Baines Johnson",
        "LBJ"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This monarch appointed Edward Courtenay, 1st Earl of Devon, royal envoy to Holy Roman Emperor Charles V but rejected his ambition for the throne. Robert Aske led a popular revolt, known as the Pilgrimage of Grace, aiming to restore this royal to the English line of succession. Phillip II of Spain used his marriage to this daughter of Catherine of Aragon as a pretext to invade the British Isles in the 1580s. The English Reformation was nearly undone by, for ten points, what \"Bloody\" queen of the Tudor Dynasty, the sister of Elizabeth I?",
      "answer": [
        "Mary I or Mary Tudor",
        "Bloody Mary"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician justified the use of force during colonization efforts in his \"Report on Algeria,\" written during Algerian occupation by the army of King Louis Philippe. This man wrote about the disconnection between the hereditary nobility and rural peasant leading to the disintegration of the Ancien Régime [[ahn-SHYAHN reh-ZHEEM]] in The Old Regime and the Revolution. This man also collected data for a book while ostensibly on a tour of U.S. prisons. For ten points, name this French aristocrat and author of Democracy in America.",
      "answer": "Alexis de Tocqueville or Alexis Charles Henri Clérel, comte de Tocqueville 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1980, this state's Lake Peigneur was contaminated when an oil rig hit a salt mine, making the water brackish. Edwin Edwards served four terms as governor of this state and won one election with the slogan \"Vote for the lizard, not the wizard\" while campaigning against KKK Grand Wizard David Duke. The \"Share Our Wealth\" program was advocated by a governor of this state whom Robert Penn Warren called a \"Dictator.\" Huey Long once governed, for ten points, what Bayou State?",
      "answer": "Louisiana"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this empire's chronology, the phrase \"the king who lived in tents\" is used to refer to its first domestic rulers, beginning with Tudiya. The practice of deporting hostile ethnic groups was introduced by Shalmaneser I, a king of this empire, following his conquest of the Mitanni. The fields of Susa were sown with salt following a humiliation inflicted by the Elamites on this empire's people, resulting in that violent act by Ashurbanipal. The city of Assur served as the capital of, for ten points, what Mesopotamian empire of Sargon II and Sennacherib [[seh-NAH-keh-rib]]?",
      "answer": "Assyrian Empire"
    },
    {
      "question": "This structure was completed in 1957 under the direction of William H. Pickering, and flooding nearly destroyed the particle accelerator chamber in which the data tapes for this structure were archived. This structure was equipped with a cosmic ray detector co- designed by graduate students in a basement of a physics building. The radiation belts that this structure discovered were named after physicist James Van Allen. For ten points, what was this first satellite launched by NASA?",
      "answer": "Explorer 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2017, the ARSA military organization launched attacks in this country's Arakan, or Rakhine, State. This country's government conducted Operation Dragon King under the orders of the socialist dictator Ne Win. In February 2021, a leader of this country, who had earlier won the Nobel Peace Prize, was overthrown in a Tatmadaw coup. For ten points, name this Southeast Asian country formerly led by Aung San Suu Kyi [[CHEE]] where over 500,000 Muslim Royhinga refugees have fled to neighboring Bangladesh since 2017.",
      "answer": [
        "Myanmar or Republic of the Union of Myanmar",
        "or Pyidaunzu Thanmăda Myăma Nainngandaw",
        "Burma 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In reference to this figure, scientist Olesya Turkina said, \"We did not learn enough from the mission to justify the death of [this astronaut].\" A monument depicts this figure cradled by hands whose digits double as rockets, a part of the larger \"Monument to the Conquerors of Space.\" Scientist Vladimir Yazdovsky trained this cosmonaut to eat a specialized gel and kept her in progressively smaller cages to prep her for spaceflight. The term \"Muttnik\" was given to, for ten points, what Moscow stray dog, the first animal to orbit earth?",
      "answer": [
        "Laika ]",
        "\"Muttnik\" before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An ancient inscription banning this event was discovered in Tiriolo, Italy in 1640. Investigations of these events were conducted by Spurius Postumius Albinus [[ahl-BEE- nooss]] and Quintus Marcius Philippus. Hispala Faecenia [[fay-keh-NEE-ah]] was awarded 100,000 bronze coins for giving her testimony about these events. The Legislation of 186 states that these events were to be overlooked by the Senate. Traditions of these events were accounted for by Livy in his History of Rome. For ten points, what unofficial festivals celebrated the Greco-Roman god of wine?",
      "answer": [
        "Bacchanalia",
        "Bachanals"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A strike against this body due to its exclusion of Polish members may have been the first-known strike in American history. A malaria outbreak affected the first session of this body, at which 22 members were present. A speech given in front of this body included one man exclaiming, “If this be treason, make the most of it!” A restored Capitol in Williamsburg is sometimes used by legislators to honor this body that was part of its state’s General Assembly. Established in 1642, for ten points, what was this early legislative body of Virginia?",
        "answer": "Virginia House of Burgesses"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The House of Burgesses became the House of Delegates after Virginia was granted what designation, held by four states? It is often denoted in the official state name of Virginia.",
        "answer": [
          "Commonwealth",
          "Commonwealth of Virginia"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Bayezid II claimed that this edict was foolish since it “[gave him the] national treasure” of one country. This edict gave rise to a “crypto” group that continued the practice it sought to ban by July 31st of the year it was ordered. A campaign conducted a century prior by Ferrand Martinez aimed to accomplish the same result as this edict, which sought to curb its non-converso population. Preceded by a number of pogroms against the Sephardi, for ten points, what was this edict which expelled the Jews from Spain?",
        "answer": [
          "Alhambra Decree",
          "Edict of Granada",
          "Decreto de la Alhambra",
          "word forms for Edict of Explusion of Jews from Spain"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Alhambra Decree was issued in this year, during which Granada fell and Europeans landed on an island briefly dubbed \"San Salvador.\"",
        "answer": "1492"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The idea for this speech came from another given by Franklin Roosevelt about “Fala.” This speech’s orator flew to Los Angeles to give this address on television, and in this speech, he encouraged listeners to voice their support for him by calling the Republican National Committee. This speech was named after a cocker spaniel given as a gift to its speaker’s children. For ten points, identify this speech given by California senator Richard Nixon regarding accusations of improper financial reimbursement.",
        "answer": "Checkers Speech"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nixon gave the \"Checkers Speech\" in the leadup to which presidential election, in which Nixon was named Dwight D. Eisenhower’s running mate for the first time?",
        "answer": "United States Presidential Election of 1952 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the 1980s, a suit was launched by McGraw-Hill against the estate of this author over royalty payments for an unfinished memoir regarding his conversations with Medgar Evers and other Civil Rights figures. This author of Remember This House challenged the Nation of Islam as being equally as wrongheaded as white supremacy in his essay \"Down at the Cross.\" Many of this man's essays, including \"The Harlem Ghetto\" and \"White Man's Guilt,\" were included in his collection The Price of the Ticket. For ten points, name this Black novelist and author of The Fire Next Time.",
        "answer": "James Baldwin or James Arthur Baldwin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Baldwin argued that this author’s character Bigger Thomas reinforced negative stereotypes about African-American men in \"Everybody's Protest Novel.\" This friend of Baldwin's wrote Native Son, Black Boy, and Uncle Tom's Children.",
        "answer": "Richard Wright or Richard Nathaniel Wright"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This object was described as “hairy and fierce” by Bartolomeo of Platina. During a campaign in Belgrade, this object supposedly led \"[mathematicians to declare] that there would follow grievous pestilence.\" This object was referred to as an “Instrument of the Devil” by Pope Callixtus III, who excommunicated it. The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle describes this object as a “portent...from the heavens” that appeared prior to the Battle of Hastings. Compared by Giotto to the star of Bethlehem, for ten points, what is this regularly appearing comet?",
        "answer": [
          "Halley’s Comet",
          "Comet Halley",
          "1P/Halley"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What American writer of travel books like Roughing It and A Tramp Abroad was both born and died in the years in which Halley's Comet was visible from Earth?",
        "answer": [
          "Mark Twain",
          "Samuel Langhorne Clemens"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ambassador made a formal petition to Boutros Boutros-Ghali to not run for a second term as UN Secretary-General, instead offering him a foundation to run, which he declined. In a controversial 60 Minutes interview, this politician said that half a million Iraqi children dying due to sanctions was \"worth it,\" though that number was later determined to have been fabricated. For ten points, name this first female Secretary of State who served under the second Clinton administration and died in March 2022.",
        "answer": [
          "Madeleine Albright or Madeleine Jana Korbel",
          "or Marie Jana Korbelová"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the last written works by Madeleine Albright was a book titled for what extreme ideology, whose American examples include the German American Bund and the Silver Legion of America?",
        "answer": [
          "Fascism",
          "Fascists",
          "Fascism: A Warning"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The creation of this state was preceded by the assassination of a military leader called the “Old Marshal.” The erroneous belief that the pope established diplomatic relations with this state is partly attributed to a film directed by Bernardo Bertolucci. That film, The Last Emperor, is about a leader of this state who ruled during the Kangde era. Harbin was the largest city in this state, where the Han formed a majority despite this state being named for a different ethnic group. For ten points, name this Japanese puppet state in China.",
        "answer": [
          "Manchukuo",
          "State of Manchuria",
          "Empire of Manchuria",
          "Empire of Great Manchuria"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Last Emperor focused on this man, the final ruler of the Qing [[CHING]] dynasty.",
        "answer": "Puyi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Gregory Tierney was the first casualty during this project, in which rocks were cleared by a group of “high scalers.” A political cartoon reading “It Can’t Be Done, Mr. Ickes [[IK-ees]]!” references the naming dispute over this project, which Six Companies, Inc. won a bidding war to carry out. Found in the Black Canyon, this structure spans both Mohave and Clark Counties and impounded the Lake Mead reservoir. Located near Las Vegas, for ten points, what is this Depression-era project named for a Republican president?",
        "answer": [
          "Hoover Dam",
          "Boulder Dam"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The original report, presented by the Reclamation Service calling for a dam on the Colorado River to generate electrical power, bore the name of Arthur Powell Davis and this Interior Secretary, better known for his participation in a scandal during the Harding administration.",
        "answer": "Albert Bacon Fall"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Election of 1984",
      "prompt": "Concerning the U.S. presidential election of 1984, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Incumbent president and former actor who won the election.",
          "answer": "Ronald Reagan or Ronald Wilson Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former vice-president from Minnesota who won only his home state and D.C.",
          "answer": "Walter \"Fritz\" Mondale or Walter Frederick \"Fritz\" Mondale"
        },
        {
          "question": "First American to orbit the Earth who lost in the Democratic primaries while serving as a senator from Ohio.",
          "answer": "John Glenn or John Herschel Glenn Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment planning to end legal distinctions between men and women which the Democratic candidate claimed he would pass if elected.",
          "answer": [
            "Equal Rights Amendment",
            "ERA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "New York representative who was the first female candidate on the presidential ticket of a major party.",
          "answer": "Geraldine Ferraro or Geraldine Anne Ferraro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wandering animal depicted \"In the Woods\" in an early Republican ad to represent the faltering Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "Bears or \"There is a Bear in the Woods.\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Wendy's slogan used by a Democrat to cast doubt on Gary Hart's proposed programs.",
          "answer": "\"Where's the Beef?\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Opening line of an ad campaign, formally known as \"Prouder, Stronger, Better,\" which depicted people happily going to work.",
          "answer": [
            "Morning in America",
            "\"It's Morning Again in America 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Portugal's Colonization Efforts",
      "prompt": "Concerning the colonies of Portugal, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Explorer who circled the Cape of Good Hope and was the first European to reach India by sea.",
          "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Their largest colony in the New World, discovered by Pedro Cabral.",
          "answer": "Brazil or Brasil"
        },
        {
          "question": "15th century treaty they made with Spain which demarcated the world into two colonial regions.",
          "answer": [
            "Treaty of Tordesillas or Tratado de Tordesillas",
            "or Tratado de Tordesilhas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City-state in Southern China, leased for 500 taels beginning in the 16th century.",
          "answer": "Macau or Macao"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in India seized by the Nehru administration in Operation Vijay.",
          "answer": "Goa"
        },
        {
          "question": "African colony that immediately descended into civil war between the MPLA and UNITA factions after independence.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Angola or República de Angola",
            "Angolan Civil War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island in the Persian Gulf conquered by General Afonso de Albuquerque to control trade in a namesake strait.",
          "answer": [
            "Hormuz or Ormuz",
            "Strait of Hormuz"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King known as \"The Fortunate\" who created the India Armadas to control the spice trade and promoted the expansion of the overseas empire.",
          "answer": [
            "Manuel I of Portugal or Manoel I",
            "or Manuel the Fortunate 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Boers",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Boers, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Port on Table Bay and one of the modern capitals of South Africa first settled by their ancestors.",
          "answer": [
            "Cape Town",
            "Kaapstad"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Language the speak which evolved from Dutch.",
          "answer": "Afrikaans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister of the UK during World War Two who was taken prisoner after a Boer ambush.",
          "answer": "Winston Churchill or Winston Leonard Spencer Churchill"
        },
        {
          "question": "British general who expanded concentration camps and appeared on World War One posters stating \"[this man] wants you!\"",
          "answer": [
            "Lord Kitchener or Horatio Herbert Kitchener",
            "or 1st Earl Kitchener"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President of the Transvaal who successfully halted the Jameson Raid.",
          "answer": "Paul Kruger or Stephanus Johannes Paulus Kruger"
        },
        {
          "question": "First prime minister of independent South Africa who fought in the Second Boer War.",
          "answer": "Louis Botha ] be lenient on pronunciation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty in which they agreed to swear fealty to Britain following the Second Boer War.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Vereeniging"
        },
        {
          "question": "Victory for Voortrekkers against the Zulu under Dingane [[dihn-GAH-neh]], which included the use of the wagonlaager.",
          "answer": "Battle of Blood River 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This occupation, which began under the Medicis in the 16th century, includes Janet Collins, who refused to work for a company in Monte Carlo since she would have had to paint her face and skin white. A group of five Native American women in this profession, including Myra Yvonne (20 pts)",
        "Chouteau and Rosella Hightower, were named the Five Moons. The short-term wife of George Balanchine, (10 pts)",
        "Maria Tallchief, held this profession. For ten points, name this profession of Misty Copeland, who became the first African-American principal of ABT after performing in works like Tchaikovsky's The Sleeping Beauty."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ballerina",
        "Prima Ballerina",
        "Ballet dancer"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this group formed the town of Jerusalem near Penn Yan and attracted young followers known as \"Universal.\" That leader of this group shunned their birth name and gendered pronouns and was known as Public Universal Friend. (20 pts)",
        "A founder of a colony of this group signed a peace treaty at Shackamaxon with the Lenape [[leh-NAH-pee]] chief, Tamanend. That man, who was given land by Charles II as debt repayment, befriended a founder of this religious group, George (10 pts)",
        "Fox. For ten points, name this Christian sect followed by William Penn."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Quakers",
        "Religious Society of Friends before \"friends\" is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Despite outnumbering an opposing force by roughly five to one, this organization lost over one-fourth of its members who participated in the Siege of Clonmel. George Monck led one part of this group with whom the Agitators and the Levellers argued (20 pts)",
        "over the form of its country’s constitution during the Putney Debates. Eschewing tents, this group often quartered in nearby buildings and employed dragoons in battles at Dunbar and Preston. Supporting the (10 pts)",
        "Protectorate, for ten points, what was this army created by the reform-minded Oliver Cromwell?"
      ],
      "answer": "New Model Army"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During an 1877 pogrom against people of this ethnicity in California, Mayor Andrew Jackson Bryant created a Committee of Safety to counter attacks on businesses like Mission Woolen Mills. After rumors that people of this ethnicity \"were killing whites wholesale,\" a (20 pts)",
        "mob killed 500 people of this ethnicity in Los Angeles in what some historians consider the largest mass lynching in American history. At least 28 miners of this ethnicity were killed in the Wyoming town of Rock (10 pts)",
        "Springs. For ten points, name this ethnicity, members of which were the subject of a namesake \"Exclusion Act.\""
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chinese-Americans",
        "Han Chinese",
        "People from China and similar answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Jozef Groll became a key innovator in this industry by using a \"noble\" ingredient produced near the city of Žatec [[ZHAH-tek]], or Saaz. A trademark dispute in this industry featured uses of the name of the city of České-Budějovice [[CHES-keh boo-DEH-yoh-vit-seh]]. Carl (20 pts)",
        "von Linde's development of refrigeration essentially eliminated this industry's use of caves for storage. One of the most important laws regulating this industry was the Reinheitsgebot [[rine-HITES-geh-boht]], which was adopted in (10 pts)",
        "Bavaria in 1516. For ten points, name this industry whose 19th century German-American titans included Eberhard Anheuser and Adolphus Busch."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Beer industry",
        "Brewing industry",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An opera by this composer includes characters such as Rambo, Molqi, and Marilyn and explores the history of Israeli-Palestinian relations, telling the story of a Jewish passenger on the hijacked Achille Lauro. In another opera by this man, quotes from the Bhagavad Gita (20 pts)",
        "are interwoven with declassified U.S. government documents about the atomic bomb. Chairman Mao dances the foxtrot in the last act of an opera by this composer about a (10 pts)",
        "president's visit abroad. For ten points, name this composer of the operas The Death of Klinghoffer, Doctor Atomic, and Nixon in China."
      ],
      "answer": "John Coolidge Adams"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Edison declared that he was afraid of this man’s discovery after one of his assistants had to get both of their arms amputated and died shortly after. An apparatus consisting of a Crookes tube and a screen painted with barium platinocyanide (20 pts)",
        "led to this scientist’s most notable discovery. This scientist’s wife reportedly exclaimed, “I have seen my death!” after examining a photograph (10 pts)",
        "of her hand. Lending his name to a type of radiation, for ten points, what German physicist discovered the X-ray?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Wilhelm Röntgen or Wilhelm Conrad Röntgen",
        "Röntgen radiation"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This movement forced Sultan Abdul Hamid II to revive the parliamentary period in 1908, shortly after this entity organized the Committee of Union and Progress. Operation Nemesis was a retaliatory mission to assassinate the Three Pashas (20 pts)",
        "of this organization, successfully targeting both Mehmed Talaat Pasha and Cemal [[keh-MAHL]] Pasha. The Assyrian and (10 pts)",
        "Armenian genocides during the First World War were executed by, for ten points, what revolutionary group in charge of the Ottoman Empire immediately prior to its dissolution?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Young Turks",
        "Jön Türkler",
        "Committee of Union and Progress before mentioned"
      ]
    }
  ]
}